Good morning, today's דף daf is כ''ז Chaf Zayin 27, where דף
daf but we will God-willing catch up by tomorrow. We pick up
at the very bottom of כ''ו עמוד ב Chaf Vav Amud Bet
last line. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan הולך ממקום למקום Holech mimakom lemakom
so we're going on the משנה Mishnah that discusses הבראה havra'ah the
meal fed to the mourners after they return, and upturned being on
upturned beds. Anyway, here we go. It says that if אבל avel
has to be traveling from one place to another. Top of
כ''ז עמוד א Chaf Zayin Amud Alef אם יכול
למעט בעסקיה ימעט ואם לאו יגלגל עמהן Im yachol lema'et be'askaya yema'et
ve'im lav yegalgel imahen if he can limit his business dealings or
his, then he should and if not he should roll with them.
So that's a very curious line, not exactly clear what it means.
Number one, the whole question is that isn't he not supposed to
be doing business dealings at all?
What's the context? Number one, and then what does יגלגל עמהן yegalgel
imahen mean? So the רמב''ם's Rambam read of it has to do
more with like or a version of תוספות's Tosafot read that if
he's traveling, you know, you gotta stop, you gotta go, you know,
buy some provisions or whatever, you're not talking about like real business.
You're talking about the types of things you need to do while
you're while you're traveling. And in that case, still, you should try
to minimize the amount that you do. But יגלגל עמהן yegalgel imahen
sort of means like, right, ideally he should, you know, try to
do it like as part with together with the group. Or I
think the רמב''ם's Rambam read of that is, you know, not limit
himself, I forget exactly I have to check, but something like limit
himself to the basic sort of needs of the journey and not
more than that. Although I'm not exactly sure how that fits in
the word יגלגל עמהן. yegalgel imahen. Okay. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan our
Rabbis taught. Anyway, it's a very terse and unclear what that means
and what it tells you about the parameters of the issues of
מלאכה. melacha. Okay. מאימתי כופין את המיטות Me'ematai kofin et hamitot back
to upturning the bed. And at what stage do you does a
אבל avel upturn the bed? משיצא מפתח ביתו Misheyatza mippetach beito so
in a way, this is also כפיית המיטות kefiyat hamitot is a
very public sign of the mourning, yet it's something which as we
know is more of is very unambiguously a practice, not just a
prohibition. So anyway, it's used as a very as they very like
symbolic sign of the beginning of the of the mourning. So it's
a way of saying, it seems like it's a way of saying,
when does the mourning begin? So once the מת met has left
the house. דברי רבי אליעזר Divrei Rabbi Eliezer not clear if that
means that the mourners are accompanying it or accompanying the מת met
or not. It would be interesting to ask whether the house of
mourning can have a state of beginning its status even before the
mourners have begun their personal practice because כפיית המיטה kefiyat hamitah is
a status that is state of the house. You know, once it's
done, it's done. It's not an ongoing practice that the mourner in
his person is doing.
משיצא מפתח ביתו Misheyatza mippetach beito presumably means yeah, I'm sorry, I
mean that the dead has left the house, and they're bringing it
to the cemetery. So anyway, that would be a maybe you're right,
maybe it means the mourners are accompanying the מת met to the
cemetery. Then even more so it's making a statement about the but
I think it means the מת met making a statement about the
status of the house maybe even presumably before the mourners have begun
their personal practices. Maybe. Anyway, it could also just mean that that's
when that that's when the mourning starts for everyone.
רבי יהושע אומר משיסתם הגולל Rabbi Yehoshua omer misheyistam hagolel no, only
after like the coffin or it's a question exactly what the גולל
golel means, but only after the מת met is buried in the
ground. מעשה שמת רבן גמליאל הזקן Ma'aseh shemet Rabban Gamliel hazaken it
was a story that רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel hazaken died. כיון
שיצא מפתח ביתו Keivan sheyatza mippetach beito once he left the house
אמר להם רבי אליעזר Amar lahem Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
said to those presumably that remained
behind כיוון שיצא Keivan sheyatza here רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel the מת.
met. He said to those that remained behind כפו מיטותיכם Kefu mitoteichem
upturn your beds. וכיון שנסתם הגולל Ucheivan shenistam hagolel and once however
the מת met was actually buried and the cover was, you know,
the coffin was sealed אמר להם רבי יהושע כפו מיטותיכם Amar lahem
Rabbi Yehoshua kefu mitoteichem then רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said to the
mourners now it's time to upturn your beds. אמרו לו כבר כפינו
על פי זקן Amru lo kevar kafinu al pi zaken they said
you're a little too late, we already did it because of what
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said. Anyway, but it hasn't resolved so which
way do we rule? We rule the latter one because of הלכה
כדברי המיקל באבל Halacha kedivrei hamikel be'avel so we rule that it's
only after the מת met has been buried. So this interests so
again whether talking about when the individual mourners begin their individual practices
or when the house gets its status, either way it begins only
after the מת met has been buried. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan מאימתי
זוקפין את המיטות Me'ematai zokfin et hamitot from what stage do you
can you do you restore the bed? בערב שבת Be'erev Shabbat what
stage can you restore the beds, can you put them upright on
בערב שבת מן המנחה ולמעלה Be'erev Shabbat min haminchah ulemalah or maybe
it means בערב שבת Erev Shabbat מן המנחה ולמעלה Min haminchah ulemalah
anyway, you put them upright leading into שבת Shabbat because we know
you don't do it on שבת, Shabbat, it's דברים שבפרהסיא devarim shebipharhesya
and even going in going even from מנחה Minchah time onwards you're
allowed to do it in terms of getting ready for שבת. Shabbat.
תוספות Tosafot of course has the question whether we're talking about מנחה
קטנה Minchah Ketanah or מנחה גדולה, Minchah Gedolah, big difference. We're talking
about like 12:30 or we talking about like 3:30. Okay. אמר רב
בר הונא אף על פי כן אינו Amar Rav Bar Huna af
al pi chen eino יושב ולעשות תחשיך. yoshev vela'asot tachshaach. And again,
here's an interesting difference
between the bed and what the person is doing. Even though you
can a person can do that in order to get ready for
שבת, Shabbat, you're not allowed to sit on it. Sitting on an
upright bed is a problem, is not allowed in terms of a
practice of אבילות. aveilut. So there's no need to allow the sitting
on the upright bed. Stand up! Or if you want to be
sitting on a bed, so you wait to turn the bed until
the last minute. Okay, but there's a difference between the getting ready
which we allow and
the person's personal practice. So A, so what is the difference? I
mean, you gotta get ready, you gotta get ready. But okay, it
takes time to go through the whole house and to rearrange the
furniture, so it just might be a need for an allowance, but
it's a limited allowance. But again, what's interested to speculate is is
there some difference between the issue of like the state of the
house? Like upturned beds is the way the house of a mourner
looks as opposed to the practices of the אבל, avel, which is
is he sitting? Is he sitting on the chair? Is he sitting
on the ground?
Both of those are two aspects of what these upturned chairs are,
and here you have them divided in terms of this status on
ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. Yes.
So two questions. One is we would normally introduce the term of
אנינות aninut here, right? Before קבורה kevura or after קבורה, kevura, but
that's absent.
Well, we're not
dealing, we can discuss אנינות aninut in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot where
it comes up. We're totally focused on when אבילות aveilut begins. Right,
the fact, but you are correct, meaning the moment אבילות aveilut begins
presumably is the moment that
אנינות aninut ends. That is correct. But we're bracketing any discussion of
אנינות. aninut.
The second thing is: why is what you do with your bed
in your house an issue of פרהסיא? parhesia?
Oh, because Michael asked that before, and
I have to stop translating it's bed, it's like couch much more.
It's like sofa.
It's all these places where people would come and see you in
the house. So therefore it's more of a פרהסיא? parhesia?
Yeah, I mean, and it's all the beds in the house, as
we're about to read. It's where people would sit, they would recline
when they would eat. Right, that would be called the מיטה, mitta,
so it would be like the divan, it would be the standard
seat of the house. So actually we're about to see that. Let's
take a look.
Yep, let's see the next line. It's like we do now with
the mirrors. Okay, we cover the mirrors of the whole house, right?
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
אמר רבא בר
הונא. Amar Rava Bar Huna. Oh no, we just did. ומוצאי שבת
אף על פי שאינו אלא יום אחד חוזר וכופה. Umotzai Shabbat af
al pi she-eino ela yom echad chozer ve-kofeh. And מוצאי שבת Motzai
Shabbat even if he's getting up from שבעה shiva on Sunday, he
still has to go ahead and re-upturn the beds throughout the entire
house.
So, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, and here we will
see how, again, it's not just what the person does, but what
the status of the house is. הכופה מיטתו לא מיטתו בלבד הוא
כופה אלא כל מיטות שיש לו בתוך ביתו הוא כופה. Ha-kofeh mitato
lo mitato bilvad hu kofeh ela kol mitot she-yesh lo b'toch beito
hu kofeh. When a person upturns his, again, let's say couch, לא
מיטתו בלבד הוא כופה, lo mitato bilvad hu kofeh, not only his
own personal one, אלא כל מיטות שיש לו בתוך ביתו הוא כופה,
ela kol mitot she-yesh lo b'toch beito hu kofeh, everything else that's
in the entire house he upturns. ואפילו יש לו עשר מיטות בעשרה
מקומות, Ve-afilu yesh lo eser mitot b'asara mekomot, and even if he
has ten in ten different places, presumably ten different rooms, or maybe
even—here's an interesting question—what if he owns ten different houses? Is there
a status of the house because that's where he's sitting,
or what if he owns it and he or she is not
sitting there? So anyway, not exactly clear. וכופה את כולן, Ve-kofeh et
kulan, all of them. So again, what we are seeing is it's
not just the practice of what this person,
what he or she is doing in terms of where they're sitting,
where they're reclining, but it's really about the entire state of the
house. ואפילו חמשה אחים ומת אחד מהן כולן כופין. Ve-afilu chamisha achim
umet echad mehen kulan kofin. Even five brothers and one died, כולן
כופין, kulan kofin, and they all four have separate houses,
each one in his or her own
house will upturn the bed. So it is a practice that takes
place in all...
they sit in one place?
That is not clear. ואם הייתה המיטה מיוחדת לכלים, Ve-im hayta ha-mitta
meyuechedet l'kelim, and again here you see that the word bed is
not exactly bed, it's like couch or something. If it's the type
of a couch that is something that you put vessels on, right,
you arrange, like you have a bench and you use it for
storing
your dishes or whatever it is, it serves like a type of
a dresser, so then: אין צריך לכפותה. Ein tzarich lichpota. You don't
have to upturn it because even again, we already learned you upturn
it even if you're not planning on sitting on it, just everything
is upturned, but only things that are made for sitting and reclining.
דרגש אין צריך לכפותו. Dargash ein tzarich lichpoto. As opposed to this
דרגש, dargash, which the גמרא Gemara will explore what that means, that
you also do not have to upturn.
אלא זוקפו. Ela zokfo. You can keep it upright. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר דרגש מתיר את קרביטיו והוא נופל מאליו. Rabban Shimon Ben
Gamliel omer dargash matir et karvitav vehu nofel me'alav. For a דרגש
dargash you can undo its straps and it will just fall apart
by itself. So now we're going to figure out what this דרגש
dargash is. מאי דרגש? Mai dargash? What is this דרגש? dargash? אמר
עולא ערסא דגדא. Amar Ulla arsa de-gada. So it is a like
a chair of good luck. So this is quite fascinating. Right? The
word גד, gad, not G-O-D but גד, gad, right, בגד, ba-gad, right,
and גד gad clearly, anyway. is in the in תנ"ך Tanach is
some sense of like some some spirit of luck. So it's funny
how it's not seen as a type of an עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara concern, but anyway, it is so he
says דרגש, dargash, I don't know where you get the gad from
here, but anyway, but maybe he's not doing a דרשה drasha on
the word, but anyway he says that this was some type of
a chair that they had that would bring good luck.
So ערסא דגדא. arsa d'gada. אמר ליה רבה: Amar lei Rabba: אלא
מעתה, ella me'ata, if that's true, גבי מלך, gabei melech, when it
comes to a king, that now we taught in the משנה, mishna,
כל העם מסובין על הארץ והוא מיסב על הדרגש, kol ha'am mesubin
al ha'aretz v'hu meisev al hadargash, that everybody reclines on the on
the ground when the king is sitting שבעה shiva and he reclines
on the דרגש, dargash, so מידי דעד האידנא לא אותביניה, midi d'ad
idna lo otvinih, it would be something that we would never sit
on ourselves until this moment, it would never be there for sitting,
you know, sort of like the כוס של אליהו kos shel Eliyahu
type of idea. It's there, but nobody drinks from it. It's there
to symbol—so here it's like you'd have a chair, but nobody would
ever sit on it. So would there be such a thing that
nobody would ever sit on? והשתא מותבינן ליה, v'hashta motvinan leih, and
now we would make the king go like lie on it and
recline on it? So מתקיף לה רב אשי, Matkif lah Rav Ashi,
so Rav Ashi asked on this, מאי קושיא, mai kushya, why is
it difficult? מידי דהוה אאכילה ושתיה, midi dehavei a'achila u'shtiya, it's just
like eating and drinking, דעד האידנא לא אוכליניה ולא אשקיניה, d'ad idna
lo ochlinih v'lo ashkiniah, until the king would be sitting שבעה, shiva,
nobody would ever think that we should be feeding him or having
him drink, השתא אוכליניה ואשקיניה, hashta ochlinih v'ashkiniah, and here that now
that he's sitting שבעה, shiva, we actually provide him with food and
drink. So maybe yes, it would be this is the compromise by
the king. We wouldn't have him recline on a normal bed, that
would be inappropriate for practices of אבילות, aveilut, but at the end
of the day he's the king, so the compromise is he does
it on this couch of luck. Again, whether that's supposed—what that's supposed
to do to the luck that it brings, I don't know. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, all right, והא ערסא דגדא, veha arsa
d'gada, if it is this couch of luck, אמאי אינו צריך לכפותו,
amai eino tzarich lichfoto, why does he not have to turn it
over?
אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא, Ella i kushya ha kushya, if I
have a question here's the question. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, baraita, דרגש אינו צריך לכפותו אלא זוקפו, Dargash eino tzarich lichfoto
ella zokfo, what we just taught, that this דרגש dargash you do
not have to upturn it, but you keep it upright. והא ערסא
דגדא, Veha arsa d'gada, if it is this couch of luck, אמאי
אינו צריך לכפותו, amai eino tzarich lichfoto, why would you not have
to upturn it? והתניא, Vehatanya, הכופה מיטתו לא מיטתו בלבד הוא כופה
אלא כל מיטות שיש לו בתוך ביתו כופה, hakofeh mitato lo mitato
bilvad hu kofeh ella kol mitot sheyesh lo betoch beito kofeh, that
not only your own couch, but it's all the couches. So even
if you're not sitting on it, it would have to be upturned.
And now of course, it's not such a question because it's a
couch that's made for sitting. This whole thing isn't made for sitting
seems to be the point, and that's what the גמרא Gemara says
back, ומאי קושיא, u'mai kushya, why is that difficult? מידי דהוה אמטה
המיוחדת לכלים, midi dehavei a'mita ha'meyuchedet l'keilim, it would be just like
the sort of the bed, the bench that's made for vessels. דתניא,
Detanya, אם הייתה מטה המיוחדת לכלים אינו צריך לכפותה, im hayta mita
ha'meyuchedet l'keilim eino tzarich lichfotah, you don't have to turn it over.
So on the one hand it's true, you don't have to turn
over its things just that you are going to sit on it,
but the only thing that you turn over are things that are
made for sitting. And we are saying that this דרגש dargash is
not made for sitting. So that would explain it, that it's made
that somehow some some, you know, some couch of luck, and it's
never—nobody sits on it and therefore it doesn't have to be upturned.
אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא, Ella i kushya ha kushya, if I
have a question here's my question. דאמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל: D'amar
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel: דרגש מתיר קביטיו והוא נופל מאליו, dargash matir
kavitav v'hu nofel me'elav, that he says what you do with a
דרגש dargash is you undo the straps and it just falls apart
by itself. ואי סלקא
דעתך, Ve'i salka da'tach, ערסא דגדא, arsa d'gada, if it's some type
of a, you know, of a couch of luck, so מאי קביטי
אית ליה, mai kaviti it leih, what do you mean what are
these straps? Like normal types of things that we have, normal types
of beds or couches or whatever don't have straps. So clearly we're
not understanding what it is. It's something that's different, not just used
differently, but something that actually is physically different than our types of
couches or, you know,
recliners. So כי אתא רבין, Ki ata Ravin, when Ravin came, אמר
ליה ההוא מרבנן, amar leih hahu merabbanan, so one of the rabbis
said to him,
ורב תחליפא בר מערבא שמיה, v'Rav Tachlifa bar Ma'arava shemih, and some
say it was רב תחליפא בר מערבא Rav Tachlifa bar Ma'arava who
used to be in—who was known in the marketplace of the גלדאי.
gilda'ei. What are the גלדאי? gilda'ei? I forgot. Leather makers.
Leather makers, thank you. Of the leather makers, which makes sense because
he's about to report on what it is and it's a type
of a thing with leather. So he said, מאי דרגש, mai dargash,
what is a dargash? ערסא דצלא. arsa d'tzalla. It is a type
of a couch or a chair or a seat made out of
leather. So it's sort of like—no, you know what it is? It's
like a director's chair. Is that what they have it? I didn't
see that. Oh, okay, they just have like a—like a piece of
leather held by straps.
I imagine—no, it's like a tent bed.
Oh, tent bed. I imagine it—I imagine it more also like a—like
a director's chair, you know, it's got like a piece of leather,
right, and you like unfold it and you got like a leather
piece like stretched out on its frame. There they don't have it
as folding, there they just have it as a frame with leather,
but now you understand why there are straps. You undo the straps
and it collapses. What you don't understand exactly is why it says
that you don't have to upturn it. Somehow because it's not a
classic couch, right? A classic couch has like, you know, I don't
know, a wooden frame and a cushion and a cloth or whatever,
it's got the straw, whatever it has, it's, you know, so this
is seen as not a normal couch and therefore it doesn't have
to be upturned. But exactly why that classifies it in a fundamentally
way, in a fundamentally different way is not clear to me. But
that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying and that's what makes it
distinct is that it's basically this like leather,
like a piece of leather that is that's the mattress, it serves
as the mattress, it serves as the base that is held on
by straps.
Where were we? Okay. איתמר נמי Itmar nami is also taught. אמר
רב ירמיה: Amar Rav Yirmiyah: דרגש סרוגה מתוכו. Dargash serugah mitokho. And
the
דרגש Dargash is the weaving or like the sort of that keeps
it connected to the frame is from within, and מיטה סרוגה על
גבה. mitah serugah al gabah. And a bed, its weaving is on
top of it. Now, first of all, it's not clear at all
how that's an איתמר נמי. itmar nami. It's just a different point
and some switched the גרסא girsa or whatever. But anyway, presumably it
means like are the straps in a bed, like if you have
the way they would make a bed is that they would sort
of do a weave of ropes around the frame, right, and that
would provide like what we would call I guess the box spring
or whatever, whatever you call it, and then on that they would
put the straw or the mattress or
whatever. So the ropes would go over the frame, right? If you're
doing a weave of the ropes, they're sort of going over the
frame in both directions and making a crisscross. Whereas apparently this you
would put a leather strap through a hole in the frame and
make a knot at the when it came on the outside, and
that's how they have the picture. So that would be that the
straps would go מתוכו, mitokho, would go through the frame. All right.
Anyway, not exactly clear how that shows that it's made out of
leather, but that is a difference. Again, why that means it doesn't
have to be upturned is not clear. Okay. So אמר רב יעקב
בר אחא אמר רב יהושע בן לוי: Amar Rav Yaakov bar Acha
amar Rav Yehoshua ben Levi: הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Halakha ke-Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. We rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. What does רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
say? Remind me
here. That was was that earlier here? Oh, that you release the
straps. Which actually is a more strict ruling, which is interesting because
it seems that as opposed to the basic rule which is don't
do anything, he demands that you actually release the straps. אמר רב
יעקב בר אחא אמר רב אסי: Amar Rav Yaakov bar Acha amar
Rav Assi: מיטה שנקליטיה יוצאין. mitah she-naklitiah yotzin. If you have a
bed that the posts go up, so meaning like imagine like a
four-poster bed, זוקפה ודיו, zokfah ve-dayo, you can just keep it upright
and that's enough. This phrase זוקפה ודיו zokfah ve-dayo is interesting. It
sounds like you actually did something, whereas basically saying you don't have
to do anything, you can keep it upright, but basically the point
is that it doesn't do anything to upturn the bed
because basically it'll be just as upright apparently when it's upturned because
the posts will keep
it won't be like it'll be suspended.
If you imagine something that's got—now I don't have my whiteboard—anyway, imagine
something that's got these tall posts and you turn it upside down,
it's actually much higher, it doesn't get lower. So maybe the whole
point is that the beds are supposed to be lowered. This is
still bizarre to upturn a bed, but it's going to be actually
higher than it was before. So he says just leave it the
way it was. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ישן על
גבי כיסא על גבי אודיני גדולה. Yashan al gabi kisse al gabi
udaiyni gedolah. If somebody sleeps—now, so again, there's a difference between what
you do with the beds and where the person actually sits or
sleeps. Both of them are required to be upturned. But again, the
beds even if
they're not being sat on have to be upturned regardless of what
the person is doing. But if this person sleeps or sits presumably,
but sleeps on a chair, on an אודיני גדולה, udaiyni gedolah, which
is like, again, like some type of a big couch, על גבי
קרקע, al gabi karka, or some have the גרסא: girsa: גדולה מכולן
אמרו אפילו על גבי קרקע, gedolah mikulan amru afilu al gabi karka,
that even a greater point they made, that even if a person
sleeps straight on the ground, לא יצא ידי חובתו, lo yatza yedei
chovato, does not fulfill the obligation. So it's not enough not to
sleep or sit on a chair, but it is actually to do
it on an upturned chair. That's even more of a sense of
I guess the world being upturned, it's something that's completely unusual. Sometimes
people will sit or sleep on the ground. Something doing this on
an upturned bed is particularly a distinctive אבילות aveilus practice. אמר רבי
יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: שלא קיים כפיית המיטה. shelo kiyam kfiyat hamitah.
What does it mean? He hasn't done anything, he hasn't fulfilled the
obligation of turning up the bed. Which again is an interesting way
of framing it because it sounds like again that it makes it,
it's not like, again, this is sort of, again, somebody mentioned בריסקר
Brisker before, right? This is the whole בריסקר, Brisker, the בריסקר's Brisker
love this סוגיא sugya because is it like the practice of the
גברא, gavra, what this person is doing in terms of his actions
or is it the sort of status of the house and the
status, the reality of upturned beds? So it's funny this little comment
on it, שלא קיים כפיית המיטה. shelo kiyam kfiyat hamitah. Why don't
you say because he has to sit on an upturned bed? שלא
קיים כפיית המיטה shelo kiyam kfiyat hamitah sounds like
there's a problem with the way the bed was upturned, right? It
doesn't sound like the
person has a responsibility where he sits and how he sits and
how he sleeps and so on. So it sounds like by doing
this, he has undermined the status of these beds sort of being
considered as upturned beds because he's not sitting on them. Anyway, it's
an interesting way of framing it. But more
simply... Both of them have to deal with these
upturned beds or couches.
Yes. Seems like there was a couple of times where זוקפו Zokfo
did not like, don't do anything but an actual activity that you
pointed out.
Yeah, earlier before right by the דרגש Dargash it said זוקפו. Zokfo.
Right.
ומה זה זוקפו? Uma ze Zokfo?
Right. Something going on there.
Yeah, I was wondering about that too. I was wondering if maybe
זוקפו Zokfo meant one of the מפרשים Meforshim definitely just says, I
think רבינו גרשום's Rabbeinu Gershom גירסא Girsah says explicitly don't do anything.
No, he actually says אין צריך לכפותו אלא זוקפו. Ein tzarich lichfoso
ela zokfo. Yeah,
it is possible that זוקפו Zokfo means to turn it 90 degrees
and not 180 degrees, to stand it up. ארחות חיים Orchos Chaim
says זוקפו Zokfo means to stand it up, stand it upright, to
turn it 90 degrees. That might make sense, so opposed
to turning it upside down.
Okay, it's possible. I'm not sure.
Right, so it's זוקפו Zokfo
sticking it but you can't turn it upside down, on its side.
Okay, that could right so that could be. I'm not sure why
the דרגש Dargash would
be, when it dealt with the דרגש Dargash and it said זוקפו,
Zokfo, it made it sound
like you weren't really upturning it. Again, I'm not sure why the
דרגש Dargash would have this, by this bed it makes sense why
it would be don't turn it flip it completely just stand it
up. I'm not sure what the idea would be with the דרגש.
Dargash. But again, maybe you're right. Maybe it's just
it's not a full bed so you don't have to fully do
it, but you need to do something. So you're probably right that
זוקפו Zokfo means here, correct, to not to leave it standing but
to make it vertical, to make it erect. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, מכבדין ומרביצין בבית האבל, Mechabdin umarbitzin beveit ha'avel,
one can sweep the floor and wash the floor in the אבל's
Avel house, ומדיחין קערות וכוסות וצלוחיות וקיטוניות בבית האבל Umadichin kearot vechosot
uztlochiot vekitoniot beveit ha'avel and can do the dishes בבית האבל, beveit
ha'avel, you can keep it looking good, right? So again, notice the
idea that you might not be able to. I mean, it's not
even that the אבל Avel is doing it because this whole כפיית
המטה Kofiat Hamittah affects the whole status of the house as being
in disarray. But even so, these types of you can keep the
house clean and neat. מהו ומדיחין את הקערות? Mahu umadichin et hakearot?
Yeah, yeah. Okay, right. So other people. I mean that would get
us to an issue of מלאכה, Melachah, but again, it's a focus
on the status of the house. ואין מביאין את המוגמר והבשמים לבית
האבל, Ve'ein mevi'in et hamugmar vehabsamim beveit ha'avel, but what you cannot
do is bring incense and aromatic spices because maybe that's a little
bit making it too nice. איני? Ini? Is that true? והתני בר
קפרא, Vehatni Bar Kappara, אין מברכין על המוגמר ועל הבשמים בבית האבל.
Ein mevarchin al hamugmar ve'al habsamim beveit ha'avel. You don't make the
ברכה Berachah on them. ברוכי הוא דלא מברכינן אבל אתויי מייתינן? Beruchi
hu dela mevarchinan aval atuya maytinan? So you don't make a ברכה
Berachah but you bring them? Interesting why you wouldn't make a ברכה.
Berachah. Okay, I mean so anyway once you're smelling it, it's ברכת
הנהנין. Birchat Hanehenin. Anyway, לא קשיא, Lo kashya, הא בבית האבל הא
בבית המנחמין. Ha beveit ha'avel ha beveit hamenachamin. No, when it says
you bring them but you don't make the ברכה, Berachah, it doesn't
mean in the אבל's Avel house, it means in the house of
the people that are providing the consolation, which is
bizarre. So why does their house get a different status and why
would you not make a ברכה Berachah in their house?
Exactly what this בית המנחמין Beit Hamenachamin is
and what is it at all and why is it that it
has this middle status is not so clear. Okay, let's take a
look now at the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay,
one minute.
Okay. And it's a real, in other words, he ends up that
the house is sort of in disarray when all the things you
sit on are upturned.
Right. But point is it's not a point of the house in
general being messy, there's a particular symbolism of the upturned bed.
Right. But it's different, you get a different feeling by covering the
mirrors, let's say. Yeah.
Because it's in the bathrooms, nobody sees it.
But it's a different association. Right. It's like you can't sit anywhere.
Right, right. That's true, because all the people visiting also don't really
have a place.
Even an interesting way of explaining בית המנחמין.
Beit Hamenachamin.
You said that the בית אבל Beit Avel is if the אבל
Avel would be sitting there on his own, a
בית המנחמין Beit Hamenachamin is a room where other people
would be, in a room where the mourner and other people would
be.
Aha. Okay, in a room that there are other people present, it's
not just the room where the אבל. Avel. Okay, that's helpful. Thanks.
Thank you. All right. Okay. So good. All right, good. So that
was the end of the כפיית המטה Kofiat Hamittah and I appreciate
the point that the כפייה Kofiah probably means to sort of put
it
upright, vertical, in those few circumstances where you don't do a full
כפייה. Kofiah. Okay. So now that we go to the next משנה.
Mishnah. אין מוליכין לבית האבל לא בטבלא ולא באסקוטלא ולא בקנון אלא
בסלים. Ein molichin beveit ha'avel lo betavla velo be'askutla velo bekanon ela
besalim. When people bring food, again now, we've seen specifically by the
סעודת הבראה, Seudat Havra'ah, but we see it's a good old custom,
a good old practice to be bringing food to the אבל's Avel
house. So they usually have much more food than they ever know
what to do with. But okay, but at least it should be
better than the opposite. So one does not bring the food to
the בית האבל beveit ha'avel in fancy types of a platter. When
people bring food again, now we've seen like specifically by the סעודת
הבראה, Seudat Havra'ah, but we see it's a good old custom, a
good old practice to be bringing food to the אבל'ס avel's house.
So they usually have much more food than they ever know what
to do with, but okay, but at least it should be better
than the opposite. So one does not bring the food to the
בית אבל beit avel in like these fancy types of platters, all
these are different like types of platters and trays and so on,
but rather in like simple, you know, baskets, woven baskets. ואין אומרים
ברכת אבלים במועד v'ein omrim birchat avelim b'moed and one does not
say the ברכה bracha for the אבלים avelim on the חול המועד,
chol hamoed, it's we've mentioned that a few times, haven't exactly spelled
out what that ברכה bracha is, it's discussed elsewhere, אבל עומדים בשורה
aval omdim b'shurah but you do have if there is a burial
on חול המועד, chol hamoed, you do have the people standing in
the rows that when the mourners, you know, come back, you know,
finish burial, then they, you know, can then they say then they
give words of consolation, ומנחמים umenachamim and then they give words of
consolation, ופוטרים את הרבים u'potrim et harabbim and then the masses are
sort of like, you know, are excused and everybody goes home. So
again, this is striking this balance that there is burial on during
חול המועד, chol hamoed, there is קריעה kriah we mentioned before and
חליצה chalitzah and, you know, סעודת הבראה seudat havra'ah for the immediate
mourners, although the practices of actual אבלות avelut are much limited, it's
really only like some of the remnant practices of שלושים, shloshim, it's
basically only דברים שבצנעה devarim she'betzina and the things that anyway would
be done on חול המועד chol hamoed so it wouldn't be obvious,
like not you know not sort of laundering and cutting the hair,
but even though the practices of mourning are extremely limited, the immediate
aftermath the immediate issues around the burial and the קריעה kriah and
so on are done as a as a in addition here to
the ניחום אבלים nichum avelim and as we've mentioned the real הלכה
halacha is that you even do ניחום אבלים nichum avelim on שבת.
shabbat. אין מניחים את המיטה ברחוב ein manichim et hamita barechov now
one does not leave the the coffin the bier in the in
the street to do a
הספד, hesped, שלא להרגיל את ההספד shelo l'hargil et ha'hesped in order
not to increase the הספד, hesped, you know, limited הספדים hespedim on
חול המועד, chol hamoed, ולא, v'lo, I mean questions about what degree
of הספדים hespedim at all, right? I mean now so is a
whole issue, I mean now we don't even do הספדים hespedim like
the whole month of ניסן, nissan, okay? So how much they are
we allowing like הספדים hespedim here is not clear, but certainly not
to increase it, ושל נשים לעולם, v'shel nashim l'olam, ומפני הכבוד u'mipnei
hakavod and women's coffins would never be left in the street presumably
even not on חול המועד chol hamoed because of respect for for
them. What does that mean? So, you know, the רבנו גרשום Rabbenu
Gershom here says that it has to do with bodily fluids if
a woman was menstruating or something, but one imagines that it's not
really specifically that, it just is again a general sense of privacy
around women and, you know, that we've already seen before relating like
around issues of קריעה kriah and so on, but it's not exactly
clear what the specific concern is. להרגיל l'hargil
to accustom people like to in order so I mean like to
like encourage is I think how I'm translating it in context.
I thought it's encourage.
Oh look at that, okay ברוך שכיוונתי.
baruch
shekivanti.
Alright נו nu look at that, מ-ת, M-T, it must be אמת
emet then. Okay, so תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan our rabbis taught,
בראשונה היו מוליכים בבית האבל עשירים בקלתות
של כסף ושל זהב barishona hayu molichim b'veit ha'avel ashirim b'kaltot shel
kesef v'shel zahav originally they would used to bring to the אבל'ס
avel's house, rich people would bring in trays of gold and silver,
ועניים בסלי נצרים va'aniyim b'salei nitzarin and poor people would bring in
baskets of what's that called like the the stuff they use like
from the palm trees, whatever those those thing what are those things
they use? Like wicker? Wicker? Okay, what's the thing they make the
לולב lulav thing out of like? Reeds? That's called wicker? Wattle? Chairs?
Like
you know the the accordion thing, yeah. Alright whatever it is, wicker
we'll say. Okay anyway, okay out of wicker basket, של ערבה קלופה
shel arava klufa or of some type of a made out of
ערבות, aravot, I don't know how you're supposed to make them out
of out of ערבות, aravot, I thought those are pretty thin anyway,
but some type of
a peeled ערבה, arava, והיו עניים מתביישים v'hayu aniyim mitbayeshim and the
poor would be embarrassed that you know that they would bring these
very plain types of things for the mourners and they'd be upstaged
by all the rich מנחמים, menachamim, or maybe when the poor were
in mourning they had poor friends and their שורבא shurva would look
so different than when the wealthy people were, התקינו שיהיו הכל מביאים
בסלי נצרים של ערבה קלופה hitkinu sheyehu hakol mevi'im b'salei nitzarin shel
arava klufa then they then they changed that everybody should bring it
in wicker out of this type of a peeled ערבה, arava, I
don't know exactly again what that is, מפני כבודן של עניים mipnei
kvodan shel aniyim in order out of respect
for the poor everybody does the same. And it also makes that
in death it's very nice as we're going to see a similar
way you know that in death sort of there's a humbleness and
everybody is sort of the same. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan בראשונה היו
משקים בבית האבל עשירים בזכוכית לבנה barishona hayu mashkim b'veit ha'avel ashirim
b'zechuchit levana
originally when they would give people to drink in the אבל'ס avel's
house, like they would give the mourners to drink, so the poor
would be the rich would be in this clear glass, ועניים בזכוכית
צבועה va'aniyim b'zechuchit tzevuah and the poor would be in colored
glass glass. Glass I guess colored glass was like a nice thing,
but basically it means apparently you know you weren't able to make
it clear which so it would
so it would not look as nice. Had impurity. Had impurity. והיו
עניים מתביישים v'hayu aniyim mitbayeshim
and the poor would be embarrassed, התקינו שיהיו הכל משקים בזכוכית צבועה.
hitkinu sheyehu hakol mashkim b'zechuchit tzevuah. מפני כבודן של עניים. mipnei kevondan
shel aniyim. So again they said everybody would do the same in
the colored glass for the, because of the poor, out of respect
for the poor. בראשונה היו מגלים פני עשירים ומכסים פני עניים, be-rishonah
hayu megalim pnei ashirim u-mekhasim pnei aniyim, originally they would, look at
this, you know, the idea of an open coffin to us seems
like, you know, oh it's so great, here it says that originally
they would show the face of the rich and cover the face
of the poor of those who had passed
away, מפני שהיו מושחרים פניהם מפני בצורת mipnei she-hayu mushkharim pneihem mipnei
batzoret because their faces would be blackened because of famine, you know
especially if it would be when people would die would be out
of lack of food often, out of starvation. והיו עניים מתביישים, ve-hayu
aniyim mitbayeshim, it would be very embarrassing. התקינו שיהיו מכסים פני הכל
מפני כבודן של עניים. hitkinu she-yihyu mekhasim pnei ha-kol mipnei kevondan shel
aniyim. So everybody's face was covered. בראשונה היו מוציאים עשירים בדרגש. be-rishonah
hayu motzi'im ashirim be-dargash. Here's our דרגש dargash again. Originally they would
take out the rich in this דרגש, dargash, ועניים בכלכלה ve-aniyim be-khalkalah
and the poor in some type of a coffin, but some type
of a, you know, of a, of a, of a bed, but
something that would not be as respectful as this
דרגש. dargash. והיו עניים מתביישים. ve-hayu aniyim mitbayeshim. התקינו שיהיו הכל מוציאים
בכלכלה מפני כבודן של עניים. hitkinu she-yihyu ha-kol motzi'im be-khalkalah mipnei kevondan
shel aniyim. Fine, again everybody would be brought out in the same
type of a bed. בראשונה היו מניחים את המוגמר תחת חולי מעיים
מתים. be-rishonah hayu manikhim et ha-mugmar takhat kholei me'ayim metim.
Originally they would put the incense underneath, the burning of the incense
we mentioned that a minute ago, but here was actually not just
in the sitting of the שבעה shivah but for the dead body
underneath the bed of the of people that died with intestinal problems
because for obvious reasons it would be very smelly. והיו חולי מעיים
חיים מתביישים. ve-hayu kholei me'ayim khayim mitbayeshim. So the people that had
intestinal problems when they were alive would be embarrassed. So it's like,
you know, like even in their death, you know, they stink and
they're, you know, treated differently. התקינו שיהיו מניחים תחת הכל מפני כבודן
של חולי מעיים חיים. hitkinu she-yihyu manikhim takhat ha-kol mipnei kevondan shel
kholei me'ayim khayim. So everybody now when they died they would sort
of burn incense. Which anyway makes sense, for an era before refrigeration
one imagines that bodies, depending on how long they were, you know,
what the weather was, temperature was and so on, having some burning
incense would probably be a good idea. בראשונה היו מטבילין את הכלים
על גבי נדות מתות. be-rishonah hayu matbilin et ha-kelim al gabei niddot
metot. Originally they
would, they would
immerse the vessels. Now literally the phrase is על גבי al gabei
on the backs of, together with, which sounds completely bizarre makes no
sense, I am assuming that what this means is like that, you
know, that belonged to women who were נדות niddot who passed away,
meaning sort of on account of נדות מתות. niddot metot. Because basically
a woman was a נדה, niddah, she passed away, so, you know,
now you want to use the vessels that she left behind in
her household but you have to be afraid that she touched them.
So what you would do sort of in terms of the dealing
with all the stuff she left behind is you'd dunk it all
in the מקוה. mikvah. והיו נדות חיות מתביישות. ve-hayu niddot khayot mitbayshot.
And then the women who were נדות niddot who
were
alive would be very embarrassed. Again, like, you know, there'd be this
whole special treatment, you know, of women who were נדה niddah when
they died, it really like singled them out, you know. And some
נדות niddot do have to stay. They do, but when a person
decides to take their own כלים kelim to the מקוה, mikvah, nobody
knows about it, it's not making this public, treating them as a
class in a different way in a very public type of a
way. So התקינו שיהיו מטבילין על גבי כל הנשים מפני כבודן של
נדות חיות. hitkinu she-yihyu matbilin al gabei kol ha-nashim mipnei kevondan shel
niddot khayot. So fine, so when all women died they would put
the כלים kelim in the מקוה mikvah afterwards so that the, so
the women who were נדות niddot wouldn't be treated differently. Of course
all women were being treated differently than all men, but that was
not a concern. בראשונה מטבילין על גבי זבים מתים. be-rishonah matbilin al
gabei zavim metim. Now we have similar thing by men. Originally they
would sort of take to the מקוה mikvah all the כלים kelim
of somebody who died who was a זב, zav, a man who
had a flow. והיו זבים חיים מתביישים. ve-hayu zavim khayim mitbayeshim. And
men who were זבים zavim had were embarrassed, again look even in
their death they're being treated differently. התקינו שיהיו מטבילין על גבי הכל
מפני כבודן של זבים חיים. hitkinu she-yihyu matbilin al gabei ha-kol mipnei
kevondan shel zavim khayim. So now we get men all treated the
same.
All men and all women.
All men and all women, all the כלים kelim in the house
are taken to the מקוה mikvah afterwards, which is pretty fascinating. What,
what? אשר אשר. Asher Asher. Yeah, well we don't worry about טהרה
taharah now. Okay look, you know בראשונה, be-rishonah, look anyway all the
כלים kelim would be טמאי טומאת מת, tmei tumat met, so you
assume it means that even כלים kelim that were handled that were
not, you know, in the house at the time of the death.
Anyway. בראשונה הייתה הוצאת המת קשה לקרוביו יותר ממיתתו, be-rishonah haytah hotza'at
ha-met kashah li-krovav yoter mi-mitato, originally the death of a person would
be more difficult to the, to the relatives, meaning the expenses of
burial would be more difficult than the death itself because the expense
would be so huge it would be so, which is, you know,
even nowadays, you know, very often people are taken advantage of in
terms of being made to feel guilty and how much money they
lay out in terms of a funeral. עד שהיו קרוביו מניחין אותו
ובורחין. ad she-hayu krovav manikhin oto u-vorkhin. So what would happen is
the relatives would just abandon the body so they wouldn't have to
pay for the costs of the funeral. עד שבא רבן גמליאל. ad
she-ba Rabban Gamliel. Until רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel the נשיא Nasi came.
ונהג קלות ראש בעצמו. ve-nahag kalut rosh be-atzmo. And he treated even
himself in a way of like lightly, you know, with terms of
the expense to be paid for his funeral. והוציאוהו בכלי פשתן. ve-hotzi'uhu
bi-khlei pishtan. And he wanted himself taken out in simple linen. linen
garments. ונהגו אחריו לצאת בכלי פשתן v'nahagu acharav latzeit b'chlei pishtan and
afterwards people did similarly and were taken out in linen garments. It's
funny which is also the idea of right the תכריכים tachrichim so
here we have covering the body, the kittel, all these things which
we think are so much like absolute Jewish practices, well they are,
but they evolved from actually quite fascinatingly a respect and a concern
for the poor, not so much out of a concern out of
a you know an issue of the dead you know the dead
him or herself but because of this larger concern for the poor.
It's also fascinatingly right it seems like the the expense was around
just how the how the dead body was apportioned, like how it
was dressed, not in terms of everything else, like you know the
box or all those other types of things, the casket. אמר רב
פפא Amar Rav Papa that even though עלמא alma nowadays the practice
is אפילו בצרדא דבר זוזא afilu b'tzerda de'bar zuza even like a
type of a cloak that just costs like a זוזא, zuza, something
extremely like simple and inexpensive. Okay what's the afilu?
Even if it's very inexpensive you still bury the body.
That's that's the practice. Not still. That's what the afilu means. Even.
Well the Gemara might say might say well that shows a limit,
you know that's really...
Even that is even that's considered acceptable or something that's done. Okay.
אין מניחין את המטה ברחוב. Ein manichin et hamitah barachov. You do
not leave the dead in the street, again in order to encourage
הספדים hespedim on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav
Papa, אין מועד בפני תלמיד חכם. ein moed bifnei talmid chacham.
There's no idea of חול המועד Chol HaMoed in front of a
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, meaning that you give a הספד hesped for
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. וכל שכן
חנוכה ופורים V'chol sheken Chanukah u'Purim and certainly in חנוכה Chanukah and
פורים. Purim. והני מילי בפניו, V'hanei milei bifanav, that's if it's in
the presence of the of the body. אבל שלא בפניו לא, Aval
shelo bifanav lo, not in his presence not. איני, Eini, is this
really true? והא רב כהנה ספדיה לרב זביד מנהרדעא בפום נהרא, V'ha
Rav Kahana sapdei l'Rav Zvid miNeharde'a b'Pum Nahara, and Rav Kahana eulogized
Rav Zvid of Neharde'a in Pum Nahara which was not in the
presence of of Rav Zvid's body? אמר רב פפי, Amar Rav Pappi,
יום שמועה הוה, yom shmu'ah havah, that was the day he heard
of the death וכבפניו דמי, u'k'bifanav dami, and subjectively for him it's
like it's in his presence. Now again this gets to the whole
subjective objective issue. It's very nice that at his subjective level he's
feeling completely torn up, but if there's an idea of כבוד החכם
kavod hachacham which overrides חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, you would think that's
not just the personal expression of grief, that's an objective reality that
it's because of the חכם chacham and the כבוד החכם kavod hachacham
that overrides and that might require the presence of the actual body
itself. So again it's a funny answer here that this subjective reality
was allowed it to be done on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. אמר
עולא, Amar Ulla, says Ulla, הספד הלב, hesped halev, דכתיב, d'chtiv, על
שדים סופדים, al shadayim soptim, so on
the on the breasts one is you know is סופדים soptim like
beats one's breast. So it's interesting because a הספד hesped we've been
talking about, you know, as the words that were said and we
had the poetry before, but here we're also getting to see some
of the performative aspects of it, that it accompanies like a beating
of the breast, a beating on the heart. So you know when
somebody would give a הספד, hesped, you know, they'd be doing like
this and presumably other people would participate as well. קיפוח ביד, Kipuach
beyad, so these are now verbs we haven't seen yet but anyway
with the קיפוח kipuach like is a type of of a clapping,
that would be with the hand, you know, not a clapping of
applause. קילוס
ברגל, Kilus b'regel, which is also a funny word, sometimes קילוס kilus
means to praise, but anyway ברגל, b'regel, that would be some stamping
of the feet, but again all of these as expressions of mourning.
We're getting a better sense of how this would be such a
public type of an event. You know which gets to the issues
of limiting הספדים hespedim at different times, like you're not מספיד maspid
all of חודש ניסן chodesh Nissan and whatever and you first of
all that expanse expansive application you don't hear here. But when הספדים
hespedim were something that was so much about this public performative aspect
and you know and this wailing and mourning and so on, you
understand why it's not appropriate for חול המועד Chol HaMoed and so
on. You know nowadays it's very challenging for for people that you
know when you hit these times where you're not supposed to do
הספדים hespedim and to give the mourners an opportunity to really get
some type of you know closure or some type of expression of
you know their feelings or remembering of the dead and that's why
you know it's sometimes this is often like observed in the breach,
it's given like lip service like okay so it's ניסן Nissan and
we don't say הספד hesped so I'll just share a few words.
So anyway but it's really you know you appreciate that it's not
such a violation if you understand that it's a completely different phenomenon
than we have nowadays and they had in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, המקלס לא יקלס בסנדל, hamakaless lo yakaless
b'sandal, so this קילוס kilus which is some type of a stamping
with the foot should not be with a sandal אלא במנעל ela
b'min'al so to be with a real shoe מפני הסכנה mipnei hasakanah
because of the danger. So what's the danger?
So Rabbeinu Gershom says that the sandal can easily more like twist
you know if you're stamping it and it'll and therefore you know
it'll you know it'll twist your leg or something.
רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel just says you know the foot is less
protected with the sandal somebody'll stamp on... stomp on your foot I
guess I don't know and you'll be less careful. He says if
you're barefoot at least you know you're barefoot you're more careful. Anyway
whatever it is it's more dangerous to do it with a sandal.
אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan אבל כיון שניענע ראשו שוב אין
מנחמין. avel kivan sheniana rosho shuv ein menachamin.
Once the mourner has like nodded his head like you know he's
sitting down and he's nodding he's shaking his head so you do
not continue to give words of נחמה. nechama. שוב אין מנחמין Shuv
ein menachamin
excuse me I misread actually. שוב אין מנחמין רשאים לישבת אצלו. Shuv
ein menachamin rashaim liyeshev etzlo. Then the mourners don't come and sit
next to him. Now what exactly is that about?
So you know רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom here sort of says שניראה
שנתנחם מעצמו shenirea shenitnachem meatzmo
like he's you know he's sort of right now consoling himself or
he makes it more sound like he's taken care of it but
you know can anybody really like you know what like like done
you know certainly during the שבעה shiva like doesn't need continued support?
But presumably means it's a signal that at this minute he's like
you know he's in himself and he's sort of in you know
and he's sort of you know and he's sort of very much
sort of like you know taking care of himself and should be
left alone which is I think a you know a very important
point cause so often people go and you know of course like
you know and and they're a little bit too much thinking about
themselves and their roles and you know rather than like what really
where you know where's the mourner holding and what does the mourner
need? Does he need me to talk? Does he need me to
be quiet? Is it time to go? Is it time to stay?
Maybe I just should sit by them and be present? Right? And
too often it's like you know so much of a focus on
what am I saying and what am I doing and did I
do the right thing and so on that it that it can
be counterproductive. So here it says you're getting a signal that the
person needs to be left alone leave the person alone.
Okay. ואמר רבי יוחנן V'amar Rabbi Yochanan הכל חייבים לעמוד בפני נשיא
Hakol chayavim laamod bifnei nasi everybody has to stand when a נשיא
nasi is present like a you know the ruler חוץ מאבל וחולה
chutz meavel vacholeh except for an אבל avel and a חולה choleh
a חולה choleh obviously they're sick have to take care of that
but an אבל avel as well is allowed presumably the point here
is is that like and it picks up on the theme before
is allowed to be in their own like private universe. Does not
have to like you know respond to the presence of like you
know of others can sort of be on their you know be
on their own. ואמר רבי יוחנן V'amar Rabbi Yochanan לכל אומרים להם
שבו lechol omrim lahem shevu for everybody you say sit you know
if they stood חוץ מאבל וחולה chutz meavel vacholeh except for an
אבל avel and a חולה choleh if they stood because a נשיא
nasi came in you don't tell them to sit because they anyway
didn't even have to stand. Another explanation is if you say שבו
shevu it could also be in the sense of like to stay
in your current state and you wouldn't want to suggest have that
type of connotation by an אבל avel and a חולה. choleh. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav אבל יום ראשון
אסור לאכול לחם משלו avel yom rishon assur leechol lechem mishelo so
this is explaining the whole concept behind or one of the aspects
behind this idea of the סעודת הבראה. seudat havrah. On the first
day cannot eat his own bread. There's a whole question of it
means the first meal or the entire first day but he has
to be fed from others.
מדאמר ליה רחמנא ליחזקאל Midamar leh rachmana liychezkel again going back to
יחזקאל Yechezkel as the source of some of the אבילות aveilus practices
God said to יחזקאל Yechezkel ולחם אנשים לא תאכל v'lechem anashim lo
tochal and do not eat the bread of people so meaning presumably
somehow being read as your own. So well actually again though presumably
presumably it means cause it's always confusing by by יחזקאל Yechezkel we
learning the opposite of what he did you know is he the
paradigm of what to do of what not to do. So it
seems to be learning here that it that here it means that
do not be fed by other people which shows you that a
normal אבל avel is supposed to be fed by by food from
other people. ואמר רב יוסף V'amar Rav Yosef מחלפי סעודתייהו להדדי. machalfi
seudatayhu lehadadi. רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף Rav Yosef presumably who were
אבלים aveilim at the same time gave each other from their own
you know from their own food. So per also maybe reflects the
fact that they again I don't I can't remember off the top
of my head if we have evidence about how whether they were
wealthy or poor. We have a similar statement interesting of course by
the משלוח מנות mishloach manot and the by פורים Purim right that
two rabbis I forget if it was רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף
Rav Yosef somebody'll have to check exchanged their meals. Like cause if
you don't have a lot of money so you have to do
like משלוח מנות mishloach manot but then to give somebody a סעודת
פורים seudat Purim but then what are you going to eat? So
you have an implicit understanding I'll give you your סעודת פורים seudat
Purim you give me my סעודת פורים seudat Purim so we both
are יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah and we're not you know you
know and it worked within our budget. So one wonders if something
sort of similar is going on here although that must you know
again they presumably they were sitting שבעה shiva at the same time.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב V'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav מת בעיר
כל בני העיר אסורים בעשיית מלאכה. met beir kol bnei hair assurim
baasiyat melacha. If there's somebody has died in the city in the
city the עיר ir is more like a town everybody in the
town cannot do מלאכה. melacha. Now that's pretty harsh because what does
it mean like everybody stops working does it mean when they're going
in order to the burial? So let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara does with this.
Why do we do it like the whole שבעה shiva right but
they're saying it's the first day?
Well it doesn't say what the limit is but presumably it means
like during the time during the time.
It says יום ראשון yom rishon right?
No אבל יום ראשון אסור
לאכול לחם משלו
avel yom rishon
assur
leechol lechem mishelo לגבי אבל. legabei avel. We do it like a
whole time don't we? We don't have the אבל avel cook during
the שבעה.
shiva. Yeah but that's out of חסד chesed that's not in terms
of the strict
הלכה. halacha. Okay but But let's even with that take a look.
רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna איקלע לדרומשא, ikla l'darumsa, he came to this
place, שמע קלי שיפורא דשיכבא, shama kali shappura d'shichva, he heard like
the shofar blast that that indicated that somebody had passed. חזא הנך
אינשי דקא עבדי עבידתא haza hanakh inishi d'ka avdi avidata and then
he saw people right after they heard that somebody had just died,
he saw people were going to work. So again you see that
the concern is doing it immediately after the death because of the
need to take care of the person who died. אמר להו, amar
lehu, he said to them, he said to them, ליהוו הנך אינשי
בשמתא, lehavei hanakh inishi b'shamta, you see we saw you had forgotten
about נידוי nidduy and שמתא shamta from earlier? No, it's still it's
still there, so anyway, so let these people be in נידוי nidduy
like in the type of a you know an we didn't say
excommunication, what word did we use before? We had a better word
that was more precise. What what did we have there? Ostracize. Let
them be ostracized. Okay. לא שיכבא איכא במתא, la shichva ika b'mata,
is there not a dead body in the city? You have to
take care of making sure the person is buried. אמרו ליה, amru
lei, they said to him, חברותא איכא במתא. chavrusas ika b'mata. No
no no, there are like here's you get the idea of חברה
קדישא, Chevra Kadisha, right? There is, you know, there's a society in
the city. אמר להו, amar lehu, so we'll see what that means
in a minute, he said, oh, אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's
the case, שריא לכו, sharya l'cho, I release you from your from
your status of נידוי. nidduy. So now what does חברותא chavrusas mean?
So could mean like there's a חברה קדישא, Chevra Kadisha, you know,
a society that's devoted to taking care of this. If you take
a look here, רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, he's interesting, he says חבורות
הן שאלו קוברין מתיהן לבדן ואלו קוברין מתיהן לבדן. chavurot hen she'elu
kovrin meiseihen levadan ve'elu kovrin meiseihen levadan.
So you have like these little senses of like, you know, these
societies, like you know you have this in some cemeteries, right? You
have, you know, people, what? לאנדסמאנשאפט, landsmanshaft,
right, so it's you know, so it's like you know each group
takes care of its own and one wonders is was that limited
to an idea of just burial or maybe these were just groups
and societies that were, you know, even when people were alive of
little sort of mini communities and when people die then they take
care of their own.
Okay, so now the Gemara says like this: ואמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, v'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, כל המתקשה על מתו יותר מדאי,
kol hamiskasheh al meito yoser midai, על מת אחר הוא
בוכה. al meis acher hu bocheh. If anybody overly, you know sort
of, you know, anguishes over their dead the person who passed, they
are really must be expressing grief over some other dead body. Now
does that mean somebody else who died in the past? We're going
to see it's going to be even more ominous. It's going to
sort of be... על מת אחר, al meis acher, for someone who's
just going to happen. Exactly. So let's take a look. ההיא איתתא
דהוות בשיבבותיה דרב הונא, hahi itta d'havas bishvavusei d'Rav Huna, so there
was a woman
that was in the in the neighborhood of רב הונא. Rav Huna.
הוו לה שבעה בנין, havu lah shiva banin, it says she had
seven sons. מית חד מנייהו, meis chad minaihu, one of them died.
הוות קבכיא ביתירתא. havas kabbakhya beyaserata.
So she would he overly was she was crying overly much alei.
שלח לה רב הונא, shalach lah Rav Huna, and I don't know
who's in a position to judge that but okay. So שלח לה
רב הונא, shalach lah Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna sent
to her, לא תעבדי הכי, lo sa'avdi hachi, don't do this. לא
אשכח בה, lo ashkakh bei, she ignored him and she didn't pay
attention. שלח לה, shalach lah, he sent her, אי צייתת מוטב, ee
tzaish mutav, listen, if you listen to me it'll be good, ולא,
v'lo, and if and if you're not listening to me, צבית זוודא
לאידך מית, tzavis zavda l'idakh meis, so you should prepare the accompaniment
or the shrouds for the other for the other dead. ומיתו כולהו
u-meisu kuleihu and then they all died. Ah, לסוף, l'sof, in the
end, אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her, צבית זוודא לנפשיך,
tzavis zavda l'nafsheikh, now you need to get shrouds ready for yourself,
ומיתה u-meisa and she died. Oh my gosh, so what a lovely
story, right? It's not.
But anyway, so look and you know given the power the Gemara
gives elsewhere for rabbis' words, is he predicting this or is he
actually causing it? But you know, but you know you can also
understand possibly a concern, so putting aside the harshness of that whole
story, you know especially in a society where it was very demonstrative
in terms of the funeral and the הספדים hespedim and all of
that, that you know how much do you want the אבילות aveilus
to be, you know, people maybe they're over you know they're being
overly demonstrative in a way that's not even a true expression you
know of their grief, you know maybe it was that type of
a concern. Like that but it's still very hard to understand these
types of these really harsh statements. Yeah, I mean if if the
woman was
just one of her sons you know or child it can really
change her life. Yeah. It's not necessarily in terms of despair I
mean. Right, sure.
Yeah, so it means it's very hard to understand the harshness here,
like you know why you know... Yeah, right.
Yeah she has other children. Right, right.
But you also suggesting though is maybe where his critique was coming
from, like that that type of a response you know you're forgetting
about the rest of your family and your other children and so
on. But no, but that's helpful to understand a little bit of
where that critique is coming from. And maybe that's what it means
על מת אחר הוא בוכה, al meis acher hu bocheh, that if
it's sort of like the whole יעקב Yaakov image, right, that he's
all for the rest of his life he's caught up in the
in mourning over יוסף, Yosef, you know you're completely forgetting about the
rest. of your family, so it's a little bit helpful in understanding
where some of the critique might be coming from. What did you
want to say, Ben?
Please. You imagine, so as you mentioned these children are very young.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Yeah. It's a bit of a continuation
of this, but it
sounded in the beginning like
an insight that if
someone is...
Right, exactly. Sounded like a psychological insight, something else must be going
on and then we say, no actually it's going to, exactly, exactly.
Okay. אל תבכו למת ואל תנודו לו, al tivku lamet veal tanudu
lo,
so according to this פסוק pasuk from ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, do not cry
for the dead and do not sort of like wail for him
or whatever, sway for him. אל תבכו למת יותר מדי ואל תנודו
לו יותר מכשיעור. al tivku lamet yoter midai veal tanudu lo yoter
mikishiur. So don't overdo it. הכיצד? hakeitzad? שלושה ימים לבכי, shlosha yamim
livchi, the first three days is real
crying, ושבעה, veshiva, the whole seven days, להספד lehespeid is the mourning,
is the eulogizing, but as we've seen the eulogizing is not only
eulogizing, it's the beating of the breast, it's other types of things,
it could be very physical expressions, but not sort of the weeping.
ושלושים לגיהוץ ולתספורת ushloshim legihutz uletisporret
and now we're getting to just practices, but it's fascinating in a
context of talking about expressions of grief, we switch gears to talk
about practices of אבלות, avelus, which frames them as expressions of grief,
right, in terms of shaving and laundry. מכאן ואילך, mikan va’eilach,
afterwards, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar hakadosh baruch hu, God is saying,
אי
אתם רחמנים בו יותר ממני, ee atem rachmanim bo yoter mimeni, you
should not have more compassion than me. So you know, like there
should be a limit.
I don't know. Okay. בכו בכו להולך, becho becho laholeich,
cry,
cry for the one going. אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda, להולך
בלא בנים, laholeich belo vanim, for one who goes without children, you
know, there you should really cry for such a person. רבי יהושע
בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, לא אזיל לבי אבלא, lo azil
levei avla, he would not go to a mourner's house אלא למאן
דאזיל בלא בני, ela leman de’azil belo vnei,
except for one that had passed with, you know, that had no
children, or
again not clear if it means that the person who died had
no children or the person had lost his children. דכתיב, dichtiv, בכו
בכו להולך כי לא ישוב עוד, becho becho laholeich ki lo yashuv
od, so
it sounds like it means that the person who passed had no
children and the person is now totally lost because they have no
descendants,
right, וראה את ארץ מולדתו, vera’ah et eretz moladeto,
and see the land of his, you know, of his heritage, but
also land of those that he has, his future generations. Somebody dies
without children, he's leaving nothing behind. רב הונא אמר, Rav Huna amar,
זה שעבר עבירה ושנה בה, zeh she’avar aveira veshana bah, and this
person,
so now we're being reading it in a different issue, if you
take a look at רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, ולא ישוב עוד, velo
yashuv od, משמע מכאן ואילך לא יעשה לעולם תשובה. mashma mikan va’eilach
lo ya’aseh le’olam teshuvah. So not just being read as this person
now is leaving nothing behind, but he's gone into a bad land
and he won't return from this bad land because he is now,
he no longer will do תשובה. teshuvah. So what is that? Somebody
who repeats an עבירה, aveira, so then you learn to rationalize it
and you're now in a type of a land that you're never
going to return from. So רב הונא לטעמיה, Rav Huna letameih, רב
הונא Rav Huna goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רב הונא, de’amar
Rav Huna, כיון שעבר אדם עבירה ושנה בה הותרה לו. keivan she’avar
adam aveira veshana bah hutra lo. A person does an עבירה aveira
and repeats it, it becomes permitted to him. הותרה לו סלקא דעתך?
hutra lo salka datach? Really? It becomes permitted? אלא אימא נעשית לו
כהיתר. ela eima na’asit lo keheter. No, in their mind it becomes
permitted. So and I told you the great line, I've said this
before, of רבי ישראל סלנטר. Rabbi Yisrael Salanter. He says and if
you do it three times it becomes a מצוה. mitzvah. So אמר
רבי לוי, amar Rabbi Levi, אבל, avel, שלושה ימים הראשונים, shlosha yamim
harishonim,
so now again we're going to this whole sort of sense of
the emotional feeling of the אבל avel and how their self-perception or
how they should be feeling or something. The first three days, יראה
עצמו כאילו חרב מונחת לו בין שתי ירכותיו yireh atzmo ke’ilu cherev
munachat lo bein shtei yarchotav or בין שתי כתפיו, bein shtei ktefav,
he should feel it like a sword is hovering between his sides,
like or is hovering in front of him. Partly what this also
reflects is an idea of being concerned like if this person died,
maybe I'm next, you know. So not just the sense of loss,
but the idea of the sword, you know,
there's an idea in the חז"ל chazal that when one person of
a group dies, everybody else should be worried. משלושה עד שבעה, mishlosha
ad shiva, כאילו מונחת לו כנגדו בקרן זוית, ke’ilu munachat lo kenegdo
bekeren zavit,
between three and seven like the sword is in the same room
but it's off in a corner. מכאן ואילך, mikan va’eilach, כאילו עוברת
כנגדו בשוק, ke’ilu overet kenegdo bashuk, and from that point on it's
like it's out there in the street. So it should still feel
this sense. Again, does that mean a personal sense of insecurity of
one's own safety and maybe they're next, or just that sense of
tragedy is present with them together in the room. All right, so
to be continued tomorrow, we are a day behind, but we will
finish this מסכת. masechet.